<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://craftplacer.moe/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://craftplacer.moe/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><updated>2022-05-30T01:46:22+00:00</updated><id>https://craftplacer.moe/feed.xml</id><title type="html">craftplacer.moe</title><entry><title type="html">The Misskey API is a trainwreck</title><link href="https://craftplacer.moe/blog/misskey-api-is-a-trainwreck" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Misskey API is a trainwreck"/><published>2022-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://craftplacer.moe/blog/misskey-api-is-a-trainwreck</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://craftplacer.moe/blog/misskey-api-is-a-trainwreck"><![CDATA[<p>Adding support for Misskey was way harder than Mastodon and Pleroma combined.</p> <p>For context, I am developing Kaiteki, my attempt at building the “best” Fediverse (and by far extension, social media) client.</p> <h2 id="the-api-breaks-several-conventions">The API breaks several conventions</h2> <p>Normally, developing API is pretty standardized because everyone is using REST. Misskey inherits the design of the <a href="https://developer.twitter.com/en/docs/twitter-api/v1/tweets/post-and-engage/overview">outdated Twitter v1 API</a> and goes beyond that. ‘How?’ you may ask? <strong>All</strong> requests are made using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">POST</code>.</p> <p>Compared to ‘normal’ APIs, you’d send a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">GET</code> request to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/items</code> to get a list of items, send a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">POST</code> request to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/items</code> to add an item to the list, and so on.</p> <p>Misskey on the other hand, uses <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">POST</code> for each request, while tacking on an action verb to the end of each endpoint (e.g. <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/items/create</code>), reminiscent of <abbr title="Remote Procedure Call, basically functions that can be called by remote appliactions">RPC</abbr>.</p> <p>Another convention that is broken is how authorization is handled in APIs. The <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTTP/Headers/Authorization"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Authorization</code> HTTP header</a> exists for a reason. It’s role is to authorize the request. Misskey instead includes the token in the request body as a field called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">i</code>. This has caused me to commit my Misskey token once due to me not knowing what that omnious <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">i</code> stood for. It’s like your maths teacher asking you to solve for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">x</code> for the first time.</p> <h2 id="schemas-lack-organization-and-are-bloated">Schemas lack organization and are bloated</h2> <p>Taking the <a href="https://misskey.io/api-doc#operation/users/show">user schema</a> as an example (which apparently uses “one of”s, which also broke ApiToDart, thanks for that) we can see an insane list of fields define when looking at <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MeDetailed</code>.</p> <p>I don’t know why the developers didn’t group flags together to another schema, so maybe they could be reused, in a more sensible way. For example, we could’ve taken <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">isAdmin</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">isModeartor</code> and put it inside a schema called something around the lines of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">UserStaffFlags</code>. The same could’ve been done for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">isCat</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">isBot</code>.</p> <p>Comparing to Pleroma, Pleroma has <a href="https://api.pleroma.social/#operation/AccountController.relationships">a schema called a relationship</a>.</p> <h2 id="the-api-is-poorly-documented">The API is poorly documented</h2> <p>Misskey’s API documentation and schemas are <a href="https://github.com/misskey-dev/misskey/blob/develop/packages/backend/src/server/api/openapi/gen-spec.ts">generated using an in-house tool</a>, which works for most cases, but not all.</p> <p>Going back to Kaiteki, I want to future-proof the code as much as possible. That means, things like having to handwrite each <abbr title="class that holds data for use across the application">model class</abbr> is a no-go. This task has been automated by me with a tool call <a href="https://github.com/Kaiteki-Fedi/ApiToDart">ApiToDart</a>, which generates code using the specifications/documentation offered by each backend.</p> <p>My solution for Kaiteki’s longevity falls apart with Misskey. There have been several issues:</p> <ul> <li>The schemas lying about whether a property is null or not <ul> <li>requires me manually specifying it</li> </ul> </li> <li>The documentation is incomplete, some fields being defined as plain “objects” with no details whatsoever.</li> <li> <p>The generated schema always assumes JSON and not other form data like multipart.</p> <div class="language-json highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="err">//</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="err">...</span><span class="w">
</span><span class="nl">"reactions"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">{</span><span class="w">
    </span><span class="nl">"type"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"object"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
    </span><span class="nl">"optional"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kc">false</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
    </span><span class="nl">"nullable"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kc">false</span><span class="w">
</span><span class="p">}</span><span class="err">,</span><span class="w">
</span><span class="err">//</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="err">...</span><span class="w">
</span></code></pre></div> </div> </li> </ul> <p>This poor documentation ends up in me sending requests over the official frontend and peeking with my browser’s developer tools. This is also how Kaiteki uses the private <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sign-in</code> endpoint which has been <a href="https://github.com/misskey-dev/misskey/tree/develop/packages/backend/src/server/api/private">explicitly removed</a> from the documentation.</p> <h2 id="will-something-ever-change">Will something ever change?</h2> <p>While I despise Misskey’s userbase, I still try to be fair about it. But the API is, like mentioned above, objectively bad. I am not the single one sharing that opinion, with a1batross (former developer of Husky) saying “at this point it’s Misskey [that] must be patched to support your client”.</p> <p>It’s as if Syuilo actively doesn’t cares about third-party applications, like Kaiteki.</p> <p>It’s easy to complain while doing nothing. But at the same time, I don’t have 100 copies of myself to contribute to every piece of software I don’t like to fix it up to the way I like it (taking Linux software as an example). Except creating an easily forgotten issue on their repository that can be easily dismissed, I don’t think there is much hope.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Hating the world"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Adding support for Misskey was way harder than Mastodon and Pleroma combined.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Distancing myself from the retro web circles</title><link href="https://craftplacer.moe/blog/distancing-from-retro-web" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Distancing myself from the retro web circles"/><published>2022-03-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://craftplacer.moe/blog/distancing-from-retro-web</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://craftplacer.moe/blog/distancing-from-retro-web"><![CDATA[<p>I don’t think I will ever join any circles about the old web. That primarily being web rings stemming from Neocities or similar. This doesn’t mean I am not interested in having some sort of partnership, but from the bigger view I don’t think I will(?)</p> <p>Similar to myself, I think I will stand on my own feet (alone?)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="microblog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I don’t think I will ever join any circles about the old web. That primarily being web rings stemming from Neocities or similar. This doesn’t mean I am not interested in having some sort of partnership, but from the bigger view I don’t think I will(?)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Keysounded mania is just launchpads for kids</title><link href="https://craftplacer.moe/blog/mania-is-launchpads-for-kids" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Keysounded mania is just launchpads for kids"/><published>2022-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://craftplacer.moe/blog/mania-is-launchpads-for-kids</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://craftplacer.moe/blog/mania-is-launchpads-for-kids"><![CDATA[<p>All you do is press 4 buttons that are dynamically mapped to sounds from a song. Literally nothing’s different.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="microblog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[All you do is press 4 buttons that are dynamically mapped to sounds from a song. Literally nothing’s different.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why I hate online social platforms</title><link href="https://craftplacer.moe/blog/hating-social-platforms" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I hate online social platforms"/><published>2022-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://craftplacer.moe/blog/hating-social-platforms</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://craftplacer.moe/blog/hating-social-platforms"><![CDATA[<p><em>… or more like, what is wrong with social media nowadays.</em></p> <blockquote> <p><strong>Preface:</strong> This blog post is a bit more <strong>insensitive</strong> and many stereotypes are being thrown around here. I think you should be smart enough to know this. Make sure you have a package of salt lying around you. In other words this is an <strong>opinion piece</strong>.</p> </blockquote> <p>Recently, I faced myself more and more depressed spending time on social platforms like Twitter or the Fediverse.</p> <p>While both of the platforms are “great” (in their own regard), I can hardly say that I enjoy them nowadays.</p> <p>I see so many stereotypes, and I’m just sick of them.</p> <h2 id="free-speech-dudes">Free-speech dudes</h2> <p>One theme I seen multiple times is the political group of people.</p> <p>While I am also interested in politics (and I do care what happens around me). Those people (especially US citizens) have the stereotype of being obnoxious about their polticial parties, even more so their US freedom of speech.</p> <p>Even if I’m not on those website like Gab, Bitchute and what not those guys use.</p> <p>And then when you check out that space, it becomes apparent that everything revolves about politicians, and nothing more. It revolves around “muh pride in mah country”.</p> <p>Similar to this, among those people, it seems okay to scream every kind of insult, because it’s free-speech right? I am allowed to say anything even if it hurts other people, because that “right”, doesn’t include having empathy to others.</p> <h2 id="imageboard-refugees">Imageboard refugees</h2> <p>While I am glad that more sacred communities exist for the more usually nerd topics – I can’t force myself to interact with someone where I get the feeling that they spend their time with users who have their heritage from boards like 4chan, 8chan or Lainchan.</p> <p>I get this eerie feeling that these people are toxic, and more <strong>often</strong> than <em>not</em>, I am correct.</p> <p>They might go around using their slang, one disagreement and they harass you either verbally or sending you disturbing content (both of which I have experienced). Another thing they like to say is “kill yourself” to everything they deem</p> <p>I scraped 4chan for fun, seeing how many people recommend Fediverse, and it truly makes me sad knowing people say that they should join it, and when they do, they mention that there are “trannies”, and what not.</p> <p>It doesn’t make it better, that Pleroma is basically the software <strong>for</strong> <em>those people</em>. You end up blocking some or many Pleroma instances just because of their user base (e.g. Poast, loli instances, etc.).</p> <p>Maybe I am being a bit sensitive, I would accept that. I stopped wanting to read slurs all day long. I won’t break down crying just because someone said I was a “faggot” or something, but I’d appreciate not having my social feed full of it.</p> <h2 id="twitter-refugees">Twitter refugees</h2> <p>One trend I saw online becoming bigger and bigger, the harder you look, are the modern LGBTQ+/snowflake-esque communities.</p> <p>You can’t go around visiting someone’s profile without seeing a generic <a href="https://picrew.me/">Picrew</a> with their sexuality flag in the background as their avatar.</p> <h3 id="biographies">Biographies</h3> <p><img src="how-a-bio-should-look-like.gif" alt="A picture with the title &quot;A bio should look like&quot;. The left side has a checkmark saying &quot;this: I like #plushies. Let's become friends&quot;, &quot;#plushies&quot; is highlighed with &quot;Interests&quot; and &quot;Let's become friends&quot; with &quot;Open for contact&quot;. The right side has a cross mark saying &quot;not this: #FuckBadPeople I am for train rights, Nerds DNI&quot;, &quot;#FuckBadPeople&quot; is highlighed with &quot;publicizing hate&quot; and &quot;train rights&quot; with &quot;political statement&quot;."/></p> <p>Even worse, when your eyes look further down, you start to read their bio which mostly consists of:</p> <ul> <li>their age</li> <li>their sexuality &amp; orientation</li> <li>politics and social movements <ul> <li>e.g. feminism, BLM, ACAB, anarchism, and similar</li> </ul> </li> <li>way too many niche things that they claim they are</li> </ul> <p>The thing is, this makes me avoid them. I am not interested in your because of your political opinion, or what movement you’re part of. It’s not you. If it is you, then I am not interested in you.</p> <h3 id="block-lists">Block lists</h3> <p>But those same people, go around making block lists with people they can’t deal with on their own.</p> <p>There are exceptions, where you might wanna say: “hmm, this person is really toxic to others, they shouldn’t be interacted with in the first place”, <strong>and this is valid</strong>.</p> <p>This also carried over cancel culture, don’t forget that. I don’t have any first hand experience with FediBlock for example. What I can say though is that the smallest insult, out of context, makes someone from Mastodon (who sees it), add you to the list.</p> <p>On the other hand though, the more people who are opposed to you are blocking you, the less headache you have interacting with them as well.</p> <h2 id="foss-bros">FOSS-bros</h2> <p>The Fediverse (primarily so Mastodon) is full of tech nerds, many of them praying to Richard Stallman or other shit.</p> <p>You as Windows user are at an disadvantage, if you are talking about your OS, because someone <strong>will</strong> talk about Micro$oft, concerns about the privacy, about how it’s closed-source.</p> <p>I for myself, expressed dislike towards the Linux ecosystem.</p> <p>Why?</p> <p>Because <strong>none</strong> of the software that this so-called community makes, is for <em>me</em>. It’s for <strong>them</strong>. For developers, not end-users. While you <strong>could</strong> use Ubuntu or Pop_OS, and be happy with it. I for the other hand am a developer, but simply not a Linux developer. I’m not into the “simple OS, no bloat” shit. I’m not them.</p> <p>And yet, people go around pushing around the FOSS-agenda, while all of their software, can’t even work in tandom sometimes, they have <strong>many</strong> rough edges, no matter if you’re talking about XMPP and Matrix, or GNOME and KDE.</p> <p>They all <strong>suck</strong>. And you can’t make them realize that.</p> <h2 id="mindless-users">Mindless users</h2> <p><img src="bot-users.gif" alt="A generic person looking at a girl inside a trash yard labelled &quot;my account&quot; holding up a &quot;meme&quot;, with them saying &quot;omg, i like this, I'm gonna follow them!!"/></p> <p>Whenever I post something on social media, and it goes rounds around the network, most users seem to forget that a bio or a user’s previous posts exist, and only press “Follow” because they one repost of a meme.</p> <p>I can hardly ever imagine those people wanting to follow me, because “I know what’s better for them”, and thus I end up rejecting their follow.</p> <h2 id="crypto-and-nfts">Crypto and NFTs</h2> <p>Crypto currency in of itself is a great concept, but the stigma became so <strong><em>bad</em></strong>.</p> <p>It started with people abusing it in ways that look like every other financial scam. Ponzi schemes, alt-coins and stocks. It’s fucking insane.</p> <p>Even worse, we got blessed with NFTs.</p> <p>I swear, it’s so annoying to hear about.</p> <p>What’s a digital ownership certificate good for?</p> <p>That you own a fucking picrew-like avatar? A fucking MONKEY?</p> <p>And beyond that, NFTs infect mainstream platforms, for no fucking reason. Just because people, and then companies, push it around.</p> <h2 id="being-sexual-as-an-entire-personality">Being sexual as an entire personality</h2> <p>One thing I faced on both Twitter and Fediverse, are people with exclusive lewd profiles.</p> <p>Maybe it’s just me feeling uncomfortable seeing those on my public feed, or clicking on this certain link (lewd alt) they put on their bio.</p> <p>The stereotype you can get from this are people, who post nudes, spread lewd illusts, or who are talking in a sexual tone publicly.</p> <p>The biggest trigger for me about this, is when they put 🔞 or <abbr title="do not interact">DNI</abbr> in their profile. And I just sit there… <em>disappointed maybe?</em> The thing is… it’s useless. You’re on the internet, and especially on open social media, it’s not 4chan, there are going to be a wide range or users, even teen ones.</p> <p>People would just say, ignore them. You’re right, ignore them. But I still don’t like the idea, how having someone who’s <em>“uwu fuck me~”</em> on Mastodon/Twitter or something.</p> <p>But even beyond that, when people indicate “fuck off minors”, then I avoid them even still being over-age by then, like it’s forbidden to be young online.</p> <p>I know that some people would say some things about this towards me. I know that – no need to tell me as well.</p> <h2 id="unable-to-have-a-discussion">Unable to have a discussion</h2> <p>One thing I saw often come around, is <strong>how tiresome it is to keep a discussion going</strong>.</p> <p>I have different opinion, for sure, and putting them out there, is sometimes so tiring.</p> <p>The reason why is that there are people, which you can’t find a common ground with, they still are against your point/stance, they keep replying.</p> <p>You end up muting the thread, because it’s just pointless, and with that comes regret.</p> <p>It’s like being on /g/ trying to convince an Arch user why Windows is good in its own regard.</p> <h2 id="superficial-users">Superficial users</h2> <p><img src="shallow-responses.gif" alt="A girl standing in the center, with 3 generic people standing around, holding signs that show &quot;:hugs:&quot;, a cuddle emoji, &quot;*pat pat*&quot; and someone without holding anything and having their mouth shut."/></p> <p>Another experience I have made is when you become open about your feelings and mood with your followers.</p> <p>I must say, most responses you get online, are tiring, boring, if not even worthless.</p> <p>I may be egoistic to expect that, but: I expect people to do better when you are feeling down. I expect people to write a <strong><em>direct</em></strong> message to you, maybe even talk to you, without their first message being <em>“are you alright?”</em>. Yeah, as if I want to reply to that. No.</p> <p>Another thing I dislike about those people is simply that they have solid advice, but what if sad me, doesn’t want to hear all about it? Being down doesn’t mean you’re the most receptable towards advice. All you want is at least some empathy, and not generic empathy like the picture illustrates, <strong>no</strong>, at least some acknowledgement and attention.</p> <h2 id="circle-jerking">Circle-jerking</h2> <p>With 2 years in the Fediverse, I realized what social groups were.</p> <p>By around 2021, I left fedi.absturztau.be, to make my own instance to be on.</p> <p>I thought this would stop all my worries back then, but now, I began to avoid the same people I started interacting with in my early days. And that’s because I started feeling out of place with them.</p> <p>All of those people keep posting about their people, make insider jokes and have generally a “closed” circle. Those same people are superficial, which make you feel ignored or not thought of.</p> <p>For me, I end up muting the entire group, just because how despicable they are.</p> <h2 id="bad-at-talking">Bad at talking</h2> <p>The most people I meet on these social platforms, myself included, don’t take any initiative to go beyond those platforms to something more direct like IMs.</p> <p>Even when they do, the conversations feel shallow, quickly dying out. Especially when the opposite has no meaningful replies. There just isn’t mutual interest.</p> <p>At the same time, I’m not the kinda person who likes being texted: “Hey, how are you? :)”, each day at an unconvenient time.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Hating the world"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[… or more like, what is wrong with social media nowadays.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Simplicity sucks</title><link href="https://craftplacer.moe/blog/simplicity-sucks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Simplicity sucks"/><published>2022-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://craftplacer.moe/blog/simplicity-sucks</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://craftplacer.moe/blog/simplicity-sucks"><![CDATA[<p><img src="graph.gif" alt="A graph with the y-axis describing the visual appeal and the x-axis describing the simplicity. The graph has a parabola-like trend with the highest point being in the middle."/></p> <p>I believe a common theme across many websites and software is the following:</p> <p>Your website is chaotic, has too much content, and simply no organization or layout. <strong>It looks bad.</strong></p> <p>Your website is full of content, but still comprehensible. <strong>It is unique from the rest and looks good.</strong></p> <p>Your website is uses a off-the-shelf stylesheet. <strong>It isn’t that special, but nobody is going to judge you.</strong></p> <p>Your website tries to be innovate and strips out so much styling, that it is literally black on white paper. <strong>Some people might like it, but it’s boring.</strong></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Hating the world"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Principles of proper web development</title><link href="https://craftplacer.moe/blog/principles-of-proper-web-dev" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Principles of proper web development"/><published>2021-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://craftplacer.moe/blog/principles-of-proper-web-dev</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://craftplacer.moe/blog/principles-of-proper-web-dev"><![CDATA[<p>When you publish something on the web there are many options, but most people are sometimes met with frustration visiting websites. Those range from the website slowly building up, interactive elements that interrupt the user, and countless others. This guide will show you the best tips towards writing a modern and lightweight site.</p> <p><strong>Note:</strong> This is not a complete HTML beginner guide, only a guide as orientation what to aim for.</p> <h2 id="dont-blindly-use-templates-or-tools">Don’t blindly use templates or tools</h2> <p>Understand what the user receives on their end, in terms of HTML, CSS and JS.</p> <p>Using a random JS powered framework for a simple site means yours going into <strong><em>trash</em></strong>.</p> <p><em>“Why?”</em>, you may ask?</p> <p>It could’ve been avoided by taking a different approach and actually save load times, improve client-side performance <del>and make some nerds who get angry over the bloated internet of today a bit more happy</del>.</p> <h2 id="build-on-html5-improve-with-css-and-enhance-with-js">Build on HTML5, improve with CSS and enhance with JS</h2> <p>HTML5 is the greatest standardized version of HTML as of yet and brings many useful features. With this, CSS should be seen as supplemental and JavaScript as optional.</p> <h3 id="writing-for-html-first">Writing for HTML first</h3> <p>A simple web page with a blog article can be done with this structure:</p> <div class="language-html highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nt">&lt;html&gt;</span>
    <span class="nt">&lt;head&gt;</span>
        <span class="nt">&lt;title&gt;</span>My great blog post - MySite.com<span class="nt">&lt;/title&gt;</span>
    <span class="nt">&lt;/head&gt;</span>
    <span class="nt">&lt;body&gt;</span>
        <span class="nt">&lt;nav&gt;</span>
            <span class="c">&lt;!-- Add navigation here --&gt;</span>
        <span class="nt">&lt;/nav&gt;</span>
        <span class="nt">&lt;main&gt;</span>   
            <span class="nt">&lt;article&gt;</span>
                <span class="nt">&lt;h1&gt;</span>My great blog post<span class="nt">&lt;/h1&gt;</span>
                <span class="nt">&lt;p&gt;</span>Great paragraph isn't it?<span class="nt">&lt;/p&gt;</span>
            <span class="nt">&lt;/article&gt;</span>
        <span class="nt">&lt;/main&gt;</span>
        <span class="nt">&lt;footer&gt;</span>
            <span class="c">&lt;!-- Add some uninteresting footer here --&gt;</span>
        <span class="nt">&lt;/footer&gt;</span>
    <span class="nt">&lt;/body&gt;</span>
<span class="nt">&lt;/html&gt;</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Structuring your site is using easy-to-understand tags like <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Element/nav"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;nav&gt;</code></a>, <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Element/header"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;header&gt;</code></a>, <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Element/main"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;main&gt;</code></a> and <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Element/footer"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;footer&gt;</code></a>.</p> <p>Using <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Element/article"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;article&gt;</code></a> tag can improve machine-readability and for example help the reader mode of your web browser recognize what part of the page is actually the blog post.</p> <p>Accessibility and machine-readability can be also improved by “perfecting” the HTML source code of your pages.</p> <h3 id="styling-with-css-second">Styling with CSS second</h3> <p>You now reached your point where you have content, but a really ugly default browser styles with Times New Roman. Congratulations. But don’t be afraid, you can change this now:</p> <p>A simple trick to get rid of the ugly font is first of all to tell our browser to use a different one with the snippet down below:</p> <div class="language-css highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nt">html</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nl">font-family</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="s2">'Arial'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nb">sans-serif</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>And ✨ magic ✨ ensues and now your page has nice sans serif text. But what does the snippet actually do? In short, it tells that the browser should use the “Arial” font on the HTML tag, that is, basically our entire page. What if we don’t have “Arial”? Our browser now sees <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sans-serif</code> which instructs it to use the next available sans serif font.</p> <h4 id="centered-layout">Centered-layout</h4> <p>Ok, alright, we got ugly font gone now, but what about layout? We don’t like reading text spanning over our entire screen. That’s also no problem, here’s a simple fix to that, a fixed-width layout:</p> <div class="language-css highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nt">body</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nl">max-width</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="m">900px</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="nl">margin</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="m">0</span> <span class="nb">auto</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>This tells our browser to constrain the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;body&gt;</code> of our page to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">900px</code> max or lower, while using the available whitespace distributed to the left and right sides, making the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;body&gt;</code> <em>centered</em>.</p> <h4 id="turning-an-ul-tag-into-a-navigation-bar">Turning an <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ul</code> tag into a navigation bar</h4> <p><a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/Layout_cookbook/Split_Navigation">This article from the <strong>Mozilla Developer Network</strong> about <strong>“Split Navigation”</strong></a>, explains everything you need to know.</p> <h4 id="keeping-it-plain-html-compatible">Keeping it plain HTML compatible</h4> <p>Don’t forget to check how your site looks <strong>without</strong> your CSS styling. Yes I’m serious. If it looks okay, go on. If it’s all over the place, you need some reworking to do.</p> <p>At this point, it’s recommended that you read more into CSS itself. Like hinted at before, I’m against frameworks, and write things yourself if you want/can. But don’t hesitate to use CSS pre-processors like <a href="https://sass-lang.com/">Sass</a>.</p> <h3 id="making-it-interactive-with-js-third">Making it interactive with JS third</h3> <p><strong>TLDR:</strong> Have strong reasons why you want to include JavaScript in your page before you do it, e.g. your site is a web-app or it makes functionality better than over old HTML form submissions.</p> <p>Now static websites are boring somewhat, but if you think about it:</p> <p>Do you really need JavaScript in most cases?</p> <p>It really depends on what your needs are: if you’d like to have fluid webpage updates because the user interacts with for example a comments section a lot, then maybe JavaScript is really the best.</p> <p>But can some work be alleviated by your backend? If the answer is yes, then you should try avoiding JavaScript at first and only use it when necessary.</p> <p>On this site, JavaScript is only loaded conditionally on some pages, like the <a href="/diary">diary page</a> or the comments like on <a href="/guestbook">the guestbook</a>.</p> <h2 id="informing-machines-about-your-content">Informing machines about your content</h2> <p>One term used throughout this guide was <strong>machine-readability</strong>. This is where we don’t want to make our source code overly complicated for machines and humans to understand, and even more want to provide extra machines information about our site.</p> <h3 id="adding-metadata-to-make-previews-on-communication-platforms-more-appealing">Adding metadata to make previews on communication platforms more appealing</h3> <p><img src="/img/blog/web-previews/discord-web-embed-with-legend.png" alt="A picture showing an embed provided by Discord with number annotations showing 1. Kaiteki; 2. Home; 3. The comfy Fediverse client; 4. (The logo); 5. (The color stripe)"/></p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Site name</strong></p> <p>Provided by <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;meta property="og:site_name" content="Kaiteki"/&gt;</code>.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Page title</strong></p> <p>Provided by <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;meta property="og:title" content="Home"/&gt;</code>.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Page description</strong></p> <p>Provided by:</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;meta name="description" content="The comfy Fediverse client"/&gt;</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;meta property="og:description" content="The comfy Fediverse client"&gt;</code></li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>Additional image</strong></p> <p>Provided by <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;meta property="og:image" content="https://craftplacer.moe/projects/kaiteki/img/kaiteki.png"/&gt;</code>.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Website color</strong></p> <p>Provided by <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;meta name="theme-color" content="#FF7890"&gt;</code>, <a href="https://developers.google.com/web/updates/2014/11/Support-for-theme-color-in-Chrome-39-for-Android">read more on this here</a>.</p> </li> </ol> <p><a href="/cookbook/website-metadata">Continue reading on this subject on the cookbook recipe “Website Metadata”</a></p> <h2 id="but-i-dont-want-to-copy--paste-everything-written-in-html">But I don’t want to copy &amp; paste everything written in HTML!</h2> <p>Seems you never heard of templating frameworks or site generators, especially static ones.</p> <p>This site is built using <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a> the most widespread solution for this sorta thing. It uses the <a href="https://github.com/Shopify/liquid">Liquid</a> templating language by Shopify. GitHub is deploying this site using their <a href="https://pages.github.com/">Pages</a> offering, with automatic “source-to-site” deployment.</p> <p>The advantages of <abbr title="static site generators">SSGs</abbr> are the following:</p> <ul> <li> <p>They get generated <strong>only once</strong> on the server or development/build pipeline and can be cached forever for everyone until updated.</p> </li> <li> <p>Visitors don’t need to run <strong><em>any</em></strong> JavaScript to make your site render, making it already one of the faster ones compared to most others.</p> </li> </ul> <h2 id="check-up-with-lighthouse-for-additional-improvement-tips">Check up with Lighthouse for additional improvement tips.</h2> <p>Chromium ships with a powerful webpage analyser called <a href="https://developers.google.com/web/tools/lighthouse/">Lighthouse</a> which can find several issues in categories: Performance, accessibility, SEO and so forth.</p> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>Don’t be lazy, put some effort in minimizing your page and use all the tools at your disposal.</p> <p>It benefits search engine ranking and mobile visitors, making your page preferred by visitors over others.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When you publish something on the web there are many options, but most people are sometimes met with frustration visiting websites. Those range from the website slowly building up, interactive elements that interrupt the user, and countless others. This guide will show you the best tips towards writing a modern and lightweight site.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Suspicious websites with Craft</title><link href="https://craftplacer.moe/blog/sus-websites" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Suspicious websites with Craft"/><published>2021-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://craftplacer.moe/blog/sus-websites</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://craftplacer.moe/blog/sus-websites"><![CDATA[<p>My website has been online for more than a year, starting off with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.github.io</code> until migrating to the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.moe</code> TLD. One thing I did was to register my website as a property on <a href="https://search.google.com/search-console">Google Search Console</a>. This allows me to see is what sites link to mine, which also exposes websites who actually scape other kinds of data. Let’s take a look together:</p> <h2 id="github-wiki-seepage"><a href="https://github-wiki-see.page/"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">github-wiki-see.page</code></a></h2> <p>This is a (in my opinion: poor) crawler for GitHub wikis (as it says on the tin). The <a href="https://github-wiki-see.page/m/Craftplacer/Kaiteki/wiki/Unable-to-login-using-Kaiteki-Web">reference</a> to my site was from one of the wiki help pages I wrote for Kaiteki. I find this kind of service highly questionable, but oh well.</p> <h2 id="stackmunchercom"><a href="https://stackmuncher.com/"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">stackmuncher.com</code></a></h2> <p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">stackmuncher.com</code> is apparently some kind of scraper for GitHub profiles apparently intended for employers. I find this annoying enough, by this <strong>not</strong> being opt-in.</p> <p>From my past experience, I already got subscribed to a company newsletter and received emails out of nowhere from someone called “Sean Bowley” from a company called “iO Associates”, looking for developers based in Germany (for some really weird reason, only Germany, with their emails containing German greetings). I had no prior contact to them, and it seems like they just scraped my profile off GitHub. Even funnier, by German law I’m not allowed to work for them, and they’d knew this if they didn’t scraped my contact in a half-assed way and instead contacted me personally, asking me professionally.</p> <p>I didn’t hear back from them after sending a reply saying exactly that.</p> <h2 id="repoarchivecom"><a href="https://repoarchive.com/"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">repoarchive.com</code></a></h2> <p>Yet another GitHub scraper.</p> <blockquote> <p><strong>About RepoArchive.com</strong></p> <p>As the name suggests, RepoArchive.com contains the archive of millions of repositories.</p> <p>RepoArchive.com does not store any data, but only uses cache data for a period of time. The idea behind RepoArchive.com is simply to give users a better reading experience.</p> <p>So while surfing RepoArchive.com, enjoy the visuality we created for some boring stuff.</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="fediverse-instances">Fediverse instances</h2> <ul> <li><a href="https://pl.veryamt.com/">https://pl.veryamt.com/</a></li> <li><a href="https://bbs.kawa-kun.com/">https://bbs.kawa-kun.com/</a></li> <li><a href="https://firebird.zone/">https://firebird.zone/</a></li> </ul> <p>Those domains are all instances that let Google index remote statuses and/or user profiles of mine. I find letting search engines index Fediverse instances highly questionable as it is privacy-invading and makes content removal harder, but that’s another topic for another blog post.</p> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>If you want your data to be scraped 10x a day, use GitHub.</p> <p>If you’re on Fediverse, expect your posts and your profile be indexed by Google, <strong><em>even if</em></strong> your instance disallows it.</p> <p>But Craft, did you really not expect to be indexed? I did, but obviously <em>everyone</em> takes a part of what content they <em>re-</em>distribute.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My website has been online for more than a year, starting off with .github.io until migrating to the .moe TLD. One thing I did was to register my website as a property on Google Search Console. This allows me to see is what sites link to mine, which also exposes websites who actually scape other kinds of data. Let’s take a look together:]]></summary></entry></feed>